Guide to the Harold Ira Martin Collection on Swindell-Dressler Company, 1940s-1970s AIS.1979.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Harold Ira Martin Collection on Swindell-Dressler Company
1940s-1970s
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Martin, Harold I.
AIS.1979.11
2.88 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Harold Ira Martin was an employee of the Swindell-Dressler Company from the 1940s to the 1970s. During his tenure, Swindell-Dressler was acquired by Pullman Incorporated. Under Pullman, the company expanded from the manufacture of industrial kilns into the engineering and construction of industrial facilities. Martin's collection documents this era of the company's history. It also includes materials related to his personal activities as a Rotarian and member of the United Methodist Church.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Harold Ira Martin Collection on Swindell Dressler Company, 1940s-1970s, AIS.1979.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
History
The Swindell-Dressler Company was formed in 1930 following the merger of American Dressler Tunnel Kilns, Inc. (builders of tunnel kilns for ceramics, founded 1915) and William Swindell and Brothers (manufacturers of steel and aluminum furnaces, founded 1850). The company's operations took on a global scope. Its services expanded into engineering and construction following its acquisition by Pullman Incorporated in 1959. In 1970, it was renamed Pullman-Swindell. In 1980, Pullman Incorporated was purchased by Wheelaborator Frye. The furnace operations were sold and the company returned to the Swindell-Dressler name, under which it continues doing business, specializing in providing services to the ceramics industry. Throughout its history, the company has been based in the Pittsburgh region.
Scope and Content Notes
The business materials series of this collection includes business reports, agreements, proposals, corporate histories, photographs of construction sites and active plants, and promotional packets from Swindell-Dressler and a few other companies in the same industry. The personal materials include a Rotary International book titled Adventure in Service, a photograph, and United Methodist Church materials. The collection is organized alphabetically, except for two folders in Series I, which were placed in Box 2 to accommodate their size, and the materials in the oversize Box 3.
Biography
Harold Ira Martin received a B.S. in Engineering from Pennsylvania State University in 1932. He joined Swindell-Dressler in 1941 and rose to the rank of Senior Vice President. He retired at some point in the 1970s.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following two series:
Series I. Business Materials, 1964-1972
Series II. Personal Materials, 1940s
Construction industry; Steel industry and trade; Kiln industry; Industries -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Personal papers; Business and Industry; Engineering; Tata Iron and Steel Company; Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation; Pullman Incorporated; Swindell-Dressler Company; Pullman Swindell Corporation
- Business Materials, 1940s-1970s; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series includes materials related to Swindell-Dressler and its industry. Materials include blueprints and transparencies of factories and furnaces, reports on projects (active and potential), proposals, informational and promotional literature, company policies and handbooks, and Martin's own handwritten notebooks. Also included are materials related to other companies in Swindell-Dressler's field, notably Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation and Tata Iron and Steel Company Limited.
  The series is organized alphabetically. However, two legal-sized folders, due to their size, are located in Box 2. The collection of aerial photographs, blueprints, transparences, and two folders of photographs are oversized and located in Box 3.
  - Application for the President's "E" Award for Export Expansion, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Challenges to the Creation and Transfer of "Know-How", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - International consultant, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - IRSID-CAFL Gas Cleaning and Recovery, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Labor-related materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Midvale-Heppenstall Project, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Constructors Association Jurisdictional Handbook, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Packets, other companies, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Packets, Swindell-Dressler, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs (cardboard backed), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pollution Survey of Industrial Complexes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Possibilities for Iron and Steel Production in the Developing Nations of the Middle and Far East in Consideration of Their Sources of Raw Material, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Preliminary Planning Report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Proposal to Armco International for the Two-Million-Ton Plan at the General Manuel N. Savio Steel Plant of Socieded Mixta Sideruigia Argentina at San Nicolas Argentina, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pullman Group of Companies Corporate History, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pullman Incorporated Retirement Plans, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Swindell-Dressler Company, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Swindell-Dressler Company, Engineering and Management Services for Iron, Steel, and Minerals Projects, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tata Iron and Steel Company Limited, Sixty-Third Annual Report, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tata photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Total Capability, parts 1-5, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Total Capability, parts 6-8, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Total Capability, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Historical, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Special Reports, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Aerial photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Blueprints, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Transparencies, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Personal Materials, 1940s; II.
  This series contains Harold Martin's personal materials. There is a copy of the Rotary International publication Adventure in Service, a photograph of him with family, and papers related to the United Methodist Church. The series is organized alphabetically.
  - Adventure in Service, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photograph, Harold Martin with family, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - United Methodist Church, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)